Finding Aid for the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities Records of Facilities at 401 Wilshire, 1980-1994, and undated IA20015
Institutional Records and Archives
Records of facilities at 401 Wilshire
1980-1994,
undated
Institutional Records and Archives
Neptune & Thomas Associates
Richard Meier & Associates
Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities
Batey & Mack
IA20015
39 Linear Feet (12 boxes, 13 flat files, 2 oversize boxes, 4 oversize architectural roll boxes)
The collection comprises architectural records, photographs, and ephemera documenting the development of the facilities and activities of the Center for the History of Art and the Humanities (GCHAH) of the J. Paul Getty Trust at 401 Wilshire Boulevard in Santa Monica, California from 1980 to 1994. The architectural records consist of blueline prints, blueprints, drawings, architectural models, reports, photographs, slides and negatives, for and of 401 Wilshire Boulevard. The photographs and ephemera document the interior spaces of 401 Wilshire Boulevard and the various activities of the GCHAH.
Acquisition Information
The items in this finding aid originated in accession numbers 1986.IA.020 (transferred by the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities); 1986.IA.021 (transferred by the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities); 1986.IA.025 (transferred by Susan Malkoff Smith, J. Paul Getty Museum Library); 1986.IA.34 (transferred by the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities); 1995.IA.01 (transferred by the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities); 1997.IA.06 (transferred by J. Paul Getty Trust); 1998.IA.02 (transferred by the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities); 2003.IA.01 (transferred by the Getty Research Institute, Andrew Werner, GRI Operations Manager); 2009.IA.40 (accessioned as part of the Legacy Appraisal Project); 2009.IA.48 (transferred by the Getty Research Institute, Wim de Wit, Head of the Department of Architecture and Contemporary Art); 2009.IA.52 (gift from Mary Sackett); and 2010.IA.47 (transferred by a former staff member).
Restrictions on Access
The records described in accessions 1986.IA.20, 1986.IA.21, 1986.IA.25, 1986.IA.34, 1995.IA.01, 1997.IA.06, 1998.IA.02, 2003.IA.01, 2009.IA.40, 2009.IA.48; 2009.IA.52; and 2010.IA.47 are available for use by qualified researchers.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection comprises architectural records, photographs, and ephemera documenting the facilities and activities of the Center for the History of Art and the Humanities (GCHAH) of the J. Paul Getty Trust at 401 Wilshire Boulevard in Santa Monica, California from approximately 1980 to 1994. The architectural records consist of blueline prints, blueprints, drawings, models, reports, photographs, slides and negatives (1980-1984, 1991, and undated) related to the 401 Wilshire building. This location was the temporary headquarters of the GCHCH, which grew out of the library at the Getty Ranch House and the Getty Villa. Plans from three architectural firms can be found in the records: Batey & Mack; Neptune & Thomas Associates; and Richard Meier & Associates.
The photographs and ephemera include a set of materials assembled to describe the role of the 401 Wilshire Boulevard building as a space for museum objects and activities while the new Getty Center in Brentwood was under construction. These materials include photographs of exhibitions and other events, event programs, event fliers, and a letter written by Musick, Peeler & Garrett (attorneys) on behalf of the J. Paul Getty Trust to the California State Board of Equalization that describes how the space at 401 Wilshire Boulevard was used for the various activities of the GCHAH. Additional photographs depict the former library at the Getty Villa; the new library, reading room, and office space of the GCHAH at 401 Wilshire Boulevard; The interiors of the facility following the Northridge earthquake (1994); and a site inspection of the Brentwood location, the site of the new Getty Center and future home of the GCHAH program. Some photographs also include staff and researchers at the GCHAH.
Arrangement
These records are arranged in two series: Series I. Photographs and ephemera, 1981, 1983, 1987-1994, and undated, Series II. Architectural records, 1980-1984, 1991, undated.
Administrative History
The Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities (GCHAH) was established in 1983 to advance and disseminate research in the history of art and the humanities. The GCHAH was one of the original programs established by the J. Paul Getty Trust, an international cultural and philanthropic organization serving both general audiences and specialized professionals. The Trust is a not-for-profit institution, educational in purpose and character, that focuses on the visual arts in all of their dimensions. As of 2009 the Trust supports and oversees four programs: the J. Paul Getty Museum; the Getty Foundation; the Getty Conservation Institute; and the Getty Research Institute, which, among other things, continues the work begun by the GCHAH.
The GCHAH opened after two years of thoughtful planning on the part of the Trust. In 1981, soon after his appointment as the first president and CEO of the Trust, Harold Williams and his team of advisors made several proposals to the Board of Trustees for programs that could be created to further the Getty's mission of "the diffusion of artistic and general knowledge," as directed by J. Paul Getty's will. The establishment of an arts library had been proposed as early as 1977 by Museum director Stephen Garrett; in February 1982 Williams' chief deputy, Nancy Englander, expanded upon Garrett's idea and outlined a proposed "Center for Advanced Study." This proposed center would include a residence program for scholars, a major expansion of the library, a limited publications program, and an art photo archive. The activities of the center would also focus on preserving historic materials in the field of art history and the development of new reference tools for the field, using the latest in information technologies. The plan was approved, and the program known as the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities officially opened in July 1983.
The GCHAH progressed quickly during its first few years. Architectural historian Kurt Forster became the first director; he was hired in October 1983 and began leading the GCHCH in the fall of 1984. In an effort to create a premier repository for manuscript collections related to artists and the field of art history at the GCHAH, Forster added the Archives of the History of Art. Not only did the Archives serve as a repository for materials on art history, but it also housed the historical records of the Museum and the Trust. In the fall of 1985 the GCHAH launched the Visiting Scholar Program, inviting 17 scholars and fellows to explore the theme "Aesthetic Experience and Affinities Among the Arts."
Due to expanded operations and limited space at the original J. Paul Getty Museum in Pacific Palisades, California, the various programs of the J. Paul Getty Trust were located at different sites throughout the Los Angeles basin during the 1980s and early 1990s. The Trust's vision was to bring together most of their programs at a single site, but until that vision became a reality, the GCHAH was "temporarily" located in the First Federal Building at 401 Wilshire Boulevard in Santa Monica, California. The construction of the new Getty Center in Brentwood took longer than originally anticipated and 401 Wilshire was occupied by the GCHAH from 1983 to 1997.
In order to fulfill its commitment to the development and diffusion of research in the history of art and the humanities, the GCHAH supported a variety of activities in resource collecting, scholarship, publications, exhibitions, conferences, and public lectures. 401 Wilshire was a "run-of-the-mill office building" that required considerable renovation to meet the GCHAH's growing need for both public and working spaces. Batey & Mack, a San Francisco firm, designed the first renovation of the temporary quarters for the GCHAH on two floors (floors 4 and 7) of 401 Wilshire. In 1991, the GCHAH expanded to occupy two more floors (floors 8 and 9), and Richard Meier & Partners, who were concurrently working on the Brentwood project, were retained to renovate the new floors. Floors 5 and 6 were also utilized, though it is unclear when they were first occupied by the GCHAH.
During its occupancy of 401 Wilshire Boulevard the GCHAH used the space as follows:
4th Floor: Library, the Archives of the History of Art (later known as Special Collections), Museum curatorial offices (which later became the space for GCHAH Publications), Mailroom, Display space for collections
5th Floor: Library
6th Floor: Photo Archives (Photo Study Collection), Scholars, and Visual Media Services
7th Floor: Administration, Museum Department of Photography, and Gallery (which was open to the public Monday through Friday at no charge)
8th Floor: Trust offices
9th Floor: Trust offices
10th Floor: Museum Department of Sculpture (which later became the space for AccAcc-Accelerated Accessions), Provenance Index, Collection Development, and Vocabularies
11th Floor: Art History Information Program and Information Technology Services
Over the years the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities experienced several significant changes. In June 1992 Kurt Forster left the GCHAH, and Tom Reese was promoted to acting director while the Trust conducted a search for a new director. In January 1994 Salvatore Settis became director of the GCHAH. In 1996, in order to avoid confusion with the soon-to-open Getty Center in Brentwood, the GCHAH was renamed the Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities. Three years later the program's name was shortened to the Getty Research Institute (GRI).
Reports; Architecture -- California -- Los Angeles; Color slides; Architectural drawings (visual works); Architectural models; Photographic prints -- 20th century; Buildings -- Specifications; Fliers (printed matter); Color negatives; Northridge Earthquake, Calif., 1994; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Blueline prints; J. Paul Getty Trust
- Photographs and ephemera, 1981; 1983,; 1987-1994,; undated; Series I.; 4.6 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  These records are arranged in no particular order.
  Scope and Contents note
  These records comprise photographs and ephemera related to the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities (GCHCH), including various photographic materials and a report compiled on behalf of the J. Paul Getty Trust. The photographic materials depict the former library at the Getty Villa; the new library, reading room, office space, and a theatrical performance at the GCHAH at 401 Wilshire Boulevard; the interiors of the facility following the Northridge earthquake (1994); and a site inspection of the Brentwood location, the site of the new Getty Center and future home of the GCHAH program. Some photographs also include staff and researchers. Loose photographs consist of 18 black-and-white photographic prints, 24 color photographic prints, approximately 390 slides, 1 sheet and 109 strips of negatives, and 19 contact sheets (1981, 1983, 1994, and undated).
  The report serves as a fairly comprehensive overview of GCHCH activities and contains materials assembled to describe the role of the 401 Wilshire Boulevard building as a space for the storage and display of museum and library holdings and scholarly research activities. The report includes photographs of exhibitions and other events, event programs, event fliers from 1987 to 1993, and a 1993 letter written by Musick, Peeler & Garrett (attorneys) on behalf of the J. Paul Getty Trust that describes how the space at 401 Wilshire Boulevard was used for the various activities of the GCHAH.
  - "The Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities, Sales Tax Audit: Vol. I, The Getty Center as a Public Space,", 1987-1993; (2 binders)
    Scope and Contents
    These records comprise a report titled, "The Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities, Sales Tax Audit: Vol. I, The Getty Center as a Public Space." The "Getty Center" in this case refers to the GCHAH building at 401 Wilshire Boulevard (prior to the construction of the Getty Center in Brentwood). The materials include photographs of exhibitions and other events, event programs, and other documentation assembled for the purpose of establishing the building at 401 Wilshire Boulevard as a public space and thereby establishing the museum and library holdings therein as exempt from sales tax. The material is prefaced by a letter written by Musick, Peeler & Garrett (attorneys) on behalf of the J. Paul Getty Trust to a representative of the California State Board of Equalization. The letter describes the role of the 401 Wilshire site as a space for the storage and public display of museum and library objects and various scholarly research activities. The letter is dated August 3, 1993 and the supporting documentation dates from 1987 to 1993.
    - Part 1 (Binder 2009.IA.40-01)
    - Part 2 (Binder 2009.IA.40-02)
  - GCHAH 401 Wilshire renovation, 1983; (2 contact sheets and 47 strips of negatives) (Box Shared 1995.IA.01; 2009.IA.52)
  - GCHAH 401 Wilshire renovation, (52 black-and-white negatives) (Binder 1986.IA.34-02)
  - GCHAH Library, 1981; undated; (11 photographs) (Box 1986.IA.25-01)
    Photographs depict the library in the Villa, unopened boxes of books in the corridor of the library in the Villa, and renovations of the new library space at 401 Wilshire Boulevard.
  - GCHAH 401 Wilshire offices prior to renovation, Center opening, and Center offices post-renovation, undated; (7 contact sheets and 24 negative strips) (Box 1986.IA.34-01)
  - GCHAH 401 Wilshire office reception area and corridor exhibition spaces, undated; (5 photographs) (Box 1997.IA.06-01)
  - GCHAH 401 Wilshire Special Collections Reading Room, staff, and researchers, 1994; undated; (24 color photographic prints, 2 black-and-white prints, 1 contact sheet, and negatives) (Box 2009.IA.48-01)
    These materials comprise 24 color photographic prints (4 x 6 inches each) and negatives of researchers and staff using the GCHAH Special Collections Reading Room at 401 Wilshire. The original envelop that contained the photographs indicates that they were developed 05/17/1994. The records also includes two undated 8 x 10 inch black-and-white portraits of Nicholas Olsberg (Head of Special Collections) and a contact sheet of other black-and-white portraits of Olsberg.
  - GCHCH Brentwood site inspection and 401 Wilshire interior and events, undated; (One binder containing 13 sheets of slides and 1 sheet of negatives) (Binder 1986.IA.34-02)
    Photographs depict GCHAH Brentwood site inspection, 401 Wilshire office remodeling/construction, and the 401 Wilshire office exterior, offices, library and exhibition spaces. Additionally, the binder includes slides and negatives of a theatrical/comical performance at the 401 Wilshire office.
  - Brentwood site visit, undated; (1 contact sheet and 10 strips of negatives) (Box Shared 1995.IA.01; 2009.IA.52)
  - Staff portrait: Bill Reider, circa 1983; (3 contact sheets and 3 strips of negatives) (Box Shared 1995.IA.01; 2009.IA.52)
  - Staff holiday party, 1993; (3 contact sheets and 4 strips of negatives) (Box Shared 1995.IA.01; 2009.IA.52)
  - Art object images, undated; (2 contact sheets and 6 strips of negatives) (Box Shared 1995.IA.01; 2009.IA.52)
  - Postcard of exterior of 401 Wilshire, undated; (1 postcard, 1 CD-ROM, and 2 photocopies) (Box Shared 1995.IA.01; 2009.IA.52)
    One original black-and-white postcard (5 x 7 inches) of First Federal Square (located at 401 Wilshire Boulevard); one CD-Rom containing two images of the postcard (front and back); Two photocopies of the postcard (enlarged to 8 x 10 inches).
  - 401 Wilshire interiors in the aftermath of the Northridge earthquake, January 1994; (approximately 50 color photographic prints) (Box 2010.IA.47-01)
- Architectural records, 1980-1984; 1991,; undated; Series II.; 19 Linear Feet (2 boxes, 13 flat files, 2 oversize boxes, 4 oversize architectural roll boxes)
  These records are arranged by architectural firm into three subseries: Series IIA. Batey and Mack, 1984 and undated, Series IIB. Neptune and Thomas Associates, 1982-1984 Series IIC. Richard Meier and Associates, 1991
  The architectural records reflect the development of the J. Paul Getty Trust, Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities (GCHAH) facilities at 401 Wilshire Boulevard in Santa Monica, California. This location was the temporary headquarters of the GCHCH program, which grew out of the library at the Getty Villa. Plans from three architectural firms can be found in the records: Batey & Mack, whose plans were used to create the space; Neptune & Thomas Associates, whose plans do not seem to have been used; and Richard Meier & Associates, who renovated two additional floors for the GCHAH in 1991. The records consist of blueline prints, drawings, architectural models, and reports, 1980-1984, 1991, and undated,
  - Batey and Mack, 1980-1990; Series II.A.; 28 Linear Feet (1 box, 6 flat files, 2 oversized boxes)
    These records are arranged by type of print and by bound set.
    Records consist of blueline prints, drawings, architectural models, and a report, 1984 and undated, created by the architectural firm of Batey and Mack for the design of the temporary quarters of the J. Paul Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities, J. Paul Getty Trust, at 401 Wilshire Boulevard in Santa Monica.
    - The J. Paul Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities Floors 4, 5, 6, 7, undated (Box 1998.IA.02-01, Folder 1)
      General note
      [Specification report.]
    - Architectural renderings:
      - Front Lobby, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
      - Floors 4-7, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
      - Corridor Desk and Chair, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
      - Corridor and Office, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
        [Copies 2 and 3 in blueline print form housed in 1986.IA.21-Flat file 2C.]
      - Corridor, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
        [Includes photocopy.]
      - Corridor and Cubicles, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
      - Corridor, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-1)
        [2 copies.]
    - Blueline/architectural drawings:
      - Floor plans:
        - Remodel Proposal Schedule, Dinwiddie General Contractor, October 15, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Fourth Floor Plan, June 1, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet Title: Title Sheet, September 21, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet #: 4.6, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Lobby Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet #: 4.9, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet #: 4.6, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Lobby Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
          [Copy 2 in Flat file 1986.IA.21-2C.]
        - Sheet #: A4.4, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, November 12, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2C)
        - Sheet #: A4.1, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Demolition Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Fifth Floor Plan, June 1, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet #: 5.1, Sheet Title: Fifth Floor Demolition Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2C)
        - Sheet #: 5.2, Sheet Title: Fifth Floor Demolition Reflected Ceiling Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2C)
        - Sheet #: 5.3, Sheet Title: Fifth Floor Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2C)
        - Sheet #: 5.4, Sheet Title: Fifth Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2C)
        - Sixth Floor Plan, June 1, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet #: 6.1, Sheet Title: Sixth Floor Demolition Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2C)
        - Sheet #: 6.2, Sheet Title: Sixth Floor Demolition Reflected Ceiling Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 6.4, Sheet Title: Sixth Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Seventh Floor Plan, June 1, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Study Room and Reception, September 23, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet #: 7.1, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Demolition Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 7.2, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Demolition Reflected Ceiling Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 7.3, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 7.4, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 7.6, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Lobby Gallery Auditorium Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 7.7, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Interior Elevators, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet Title: Title Sheet, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: A7.1, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Demolition Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: A7.2, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Demolition Reflected Ceiling Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: A7.4, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Reflected Ceiling Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: 7.6, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Lobby Gallery Auditorium Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet Title: Workstation Plan, September 10, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
      - Furniture plans:
        - Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Archival Shelving Storage Layout, July 19, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Cabinetry Layout, November 28, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet #: 4, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: 4.5, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet #: 4.8, Sheet Title: Fourth Floor Shelving Layout, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet #: 5, Sheet Title: Fifth Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: 6.3, Sheet Title: Sixth Floor Lounge Furniture Plan, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2B)
        - Sheet #: 6, Sheet Title: Sixth Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: 6.3, Sheet Title: Sixth Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Cabinetry Layout, November 28, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-2A)
        - Sheet #: A7.5, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3A)
        - Sheet #: 7.5, Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Furniture Plan, September 22, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Reception Desk, September 23, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Auditorium Columns and Cabinets, September 23, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Auditorium Projection Screen, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
        - Sheet Title: Seventh Floor Kitchen Plans and Audio Visual Projection Cabinet, September 19, 1984 (Flatfile 1986.IA.21-3B)
      - Utilities plans: